Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999 RL.00607
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Rwanda Audiotapes Series (Audiocassette), 1993-1994, 8 boxes
  - AV/917, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW071)
    The reporter then asks Niyitegeka to respond to RPF appeals to the population to fight against the "government of killers." Niyitegeka denies the charges and claims that in Kigali only RPF soldiers were killed, and that this was after they infiltrated the Presidential Guard compound. Niyitegeka admits that the Presidential Guard was responsible for violence in the immediate wake of the President's assassination but asserts that this violence did not come on orders from the army, but as a result of the Presidential Guard's justifiable "anger and fury" at the murder of their President.
    Niyitegeka then explains the Inkotanyi's motives for violence: they are furious because they mistakenly believed that assassinating the President would allow them to "enthrone" their own leader.
    Niyitegeka's final remarks regard the RPF's alleged unwillingness to sign a cease-fire or abide by the Arusha accords.
    Following the interview, there is a report on the death of Major General Nsabimana Déogratias — he was on Habyarimana's plane — and the cabinet's choice for replacement, Colonel Bizimungu Augustin. The journalist explains that promotions in the army are based on soldiers' "competence, work, courage at work and at the front."
    Tape stresses need for population to show its "courage" by collaborating with the army and local officials in "ensuring security " against the "enemy."
    In an interview with Hyancinthe Bicamumpaka, Elieser Niyitegeka (Minister of Information) lauds the population's bravery in fighting alongside the army and accuses "Inkotanyi" of atrocities which violate the population's rights.
  - AV/918, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW072A)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 17
    This broadcast begins with a series of news bulletins. They are followed by Nsengiyumva's interview of Froduald Karamira of the MDR. Karamira addresses the people of Kigali and instructs them to assist the Army by carrying out their assigned duties and staying within their respective quarters. He goes on to say that the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) has infiltrated itself into the civilian population which accounts for the deaths of so many non-soldiers. Major General Bizimana's speech is then broadcasted. He makes a call to Rwandans to respect their local authorities. Nizeyimana then gives an update on the war which includes a direct call against Mutarekanwa, a barrister in the Rugenge sector.
  - AV/918, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW072B)
    This broadcast begins with a news bulletin. Nsengiyumva follows with an update of the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and FAR movements. A speech by President Sindikubwabo is next. He calls on Rwandans to collaborate with the government and assist in denouncing "criminals" that continue to trouble the peace. An unidentified journalist then continues with the news which includes reports of the UNAMIR's role in setting up negotiations and the departure of the Belgian contingent. The tape ends with Kagina reporting that Simbizi of the CDR blames the Belgians for some of the country's trouble.
  - AV/919, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW073)
    Cette cassette commence avec un discours du Président Sindikubwabo. Il demande à la population de ne pas permettre à l'ennemi de semer la discorde parmi eux. Il demande aussi aux sevices adminstratives de suivre le problème de sécurité de très près. Niyitegeka annonce ensuite que le Préfet de Butare est désormais remplcé par Sylvain Nsabimana. L'Archevêque de Kigali prend la parole et déclare que les attaques du FPR sont la cause de la discorde entre les Hutu et Tutsi. Un journaliste non-identifié annonce ensuite l'installation des barrières et l'instauration despatrouilles nocturnes pour empêcher l'infiltration des "malfaiteurs." La cassette se termine avec une discussion entre Mukarutamu, Murego, du MDR; Mugenzi, du PL; Nsengiyumva, du PSD et Ngirumpatse, du PSD. Les thèmes de la discussion sont: (1) cette guerre est le travail d'un groupe de réfugiés de la révolution de 1959 qui n'ont pas changé de mentalité et veulent absolutement accéder au pouvoir, (2) ils veulent restaurer la monarchie de leurs ancêtres, (3) il est dangereux d'ignorer l'ethnie, il faut accepter qu'il existe un problème d'ethnie, (4) le FPR a compris que l'instauration des Accords d'Arusha ne leur permettrait pas de régner seul donc ils ont préféré la guerre.
  - AV/920, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW074A)
    Side A consists of a discussion hosted by Agensta Mukarutama featuring Murego, Ngirumpatse, Nsengiyumva, and Mugenzi.
    Murego begins with a monologue arguing, (1) that people are beginning to recognize that the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF)'s goal is to return Rwanda to its pre-revolutionary time in which "some people commanded... and others obeyed," (2) that the RPF was deluded and "made a mistake" in thinking that it could dominate as before, (3) that Rwandans have learned their history and are "saying 'no'" to a repetition of history and are "resisting en masse" the RPF's attempt to "'live handsomely at the expense of his subordinates,'" (4) and that "Rwandans will never again…be a people of slaves."
    Agenesta Mukarutama then continues along the same lines suggesting that the RPF has brought the current hardship upon itself, having fallen "victim to its [own] illusions," and that the "Tutsi" could have predicted that this "socio-political disaster" would follow from their attempt to bring back apartheid.
    Murego then asserts that, unsatisfied with the right of return offered by the Arusha Accords, the RPF wanted "conquest and revenge," wanted "to massacre their fellows [and] enslave a people who has said 'no' to slavery."
    Mukarutama then introduces Ngirumpatse, MRND President, who argues (1) that it would be a "mistake" to think the "Revolutions [of 1959] was finished once and for all," (2) that in this respect, the Arusha Accords were an exceptional attempt on the part of Rwandans to prevent a repetition of history.
    Ngirumpatse continues by stressing the exceptional generosity of the Arusha Accords and suggesting that the RPF's stubbornly monarchist desire for domination prevents it from accepting these accords.
    Ngirumpatse then asserts that the future of the Arusha Accords depends on the RPF and that as long as it continues to "provoke war" (1) Rwandans will defend themselves, (2) that the RPF's attacks are making Ngirumaptse fear the day when the "minority" sends the "majority of the population" "to the bush," (3) and that this fear explains the desire to see "the minority... deleted from the face of the country."
    Nsengiyumva then echoes Ngirumpatse's appeal to the RPF to abide by the Arusha Accords.
    In an exchange with Mukarutamu, Mugenzi then suggests (1) that both the RPF and the international community were "warned" of the "disaster" that could ensue if the RPF did not abide by the Arusha Accords and so are "responsible" for what has happened, (2) and that negotiations have been made even more difficult by the President's "assassination" and the "fear" and "fury" that it has generated among the Rwandan people.
    Next, Ngirumpatse defends the Rwandan government against charges that it is constitutionally invalid. In the course of his defense, Ngirumpatse again refers to RPF "illusions."
    Mugenzi then suggests (1) that the international community is largely "responsible" (this word is repeated many times) for the "socio-political disorder" that some journalist call "barbarity." (2) that the international community was "responsible" for allowing the unchecked "infiltration of RPF agents and soldiers in different quarters of Kigali," (3) that the President's assassination by the RPF bears witness to the UNAMIR's faulty surveillance, (4) that he, Mugenzi, warned several UN ambassadors that their treatment of the RPF was unacceptable and threatened to bring about events for which the UN would be "responsible."
    Repeating the word "responsibility," Mukarutamu asks Ngirumpatse to say more about the Belgian contingent's role.
    Ngirumpatse "denounces" the international community's role in the "disaster," alleging that in the UNAMIR and Belgian controlled regions of Kirambo and Mutura the RPF was allowed "to kill the population," including politicians like Gatabazi Felicien and Bucyana.
    Transmission identity needs to be confirmed
    In this round table discussion hosted by Agensta Mukarutama featuring Murego, Ngirumpatse, Nsengiyumva, and Mugenzi, the participants discuss RPF plans to return Rwanda to its pre-revolutionary state in which the minority enslaved the majority. The speakers suggest that both the RPF and the international community were warned about the consequences of an RPF attack and so are now responsible for Rwanda's "socio-political disaster."
  - AV/920, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW074B)
    Continuing the discussion that ends side A, Ngirumpatse (1) suggests that the Belgians collaborated in the President's assassination, (2) asserts Belgians were seen fighting on the side of the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and firing at Rwandan soldiers and (3) concludes that the Belgians and UNAMIR bear "responsibility" for the "disaster."
    In response, Mukarutamu says it is "curious that Belgium gets bogged down every time there are problems between Hutus and Tutsis."
    Murego explains that the UN is "responsible" for the situation in Rwanda because (1) it favored the RPF, (2) allowed the RPF to commit assassinations, (3) was insensitive to the rights of "the Rwandan people."
    Murego goes on to suggest that (1) the Belgians act as though they wish "to conquer the country again, (2) that though they may soon leave, this does not "cancel the judgment" made upon them, (3) that some Belgians have decided to side "with the RPF to harm Rwanda and the Rwandans," (4) that some of these Belgians might have been killed in a fire fight. Murego concludes by saying that "Rwanda became an independent country that nobody can invade."
    Responding to a further question about the role of the Belgians, Ngirumpatse suggests (1) that Belgians think of Rwandans as exceedingly polite and try to take advantage of this, (2) that some Rwandan political parties tried to strengthen Belgium's influence in Rwanda, (3) that if Rwandan's aren't more careful people will confuse their "docility" with a lack of self-determination, (4) and that submitting to the RPF "hands and feet tied" will bring not bring prosperity to Rwandans. Ngirumpatse concludes by suggesting that Rwandans should be more like the Roman emperor who understood that it was better to be feared than liked.
    Next, in an exchange with Mukarutama, Ngirumpatse discusses Ugandan reaction to the current events, charging that Museveni (1) helped the RPF wreak havoc in Kigali and elsewhere, (2) and that he did not respect or understand that Rwandan people had killed because of anger over their President's assassination. Ngirumpatse also criticized the hypocrisy of the international community because it does not condemn the human rights violations perpetrated in Uganda. Finally, Ngirumpatse predicts that before too long Museveni will have Rwanda type "problem."
    Dr. Murego ends the "debate" by highlighting its main points: (1) that the "Rwandan people's... fierce defense" demonstrates a refusal to "any longer be unconditionally docile" and a desire "to be in control of their own destiny," (2) that a new step is being taken to complete the Revolution of 1959, wherein the Rwandan people are not liberating themselves from "bad physical leadership" but from those related "to the family or ethnicity of those leaders," (3) that the latter signals a "mental revolution" because it shows that the Rwandan people "will never stand anymore to be anyone's slaves," (4) that this revolution will ensure that the "docility" (this word is often repeated) attributed to the Rwandan people will never again be used to humiliate them and deprive them of their rights, (5) that this is a way of saying "'no' to any dictatorial" intentions of the enemy.
    Mukarutamu ends the broadcast by thanking her guests and calling on the Rwandan people to "control their destiny…defend their right to dignity... [and to be] vigilant and intelligent."
    In the second half of this round table discussion hosted by Agensta Mukarutama featuring Murego, Ngirumpatse, Nsengiyumva, and Mugenzi, the participants focus on the Belgians and their "responsibility" for the "disaster" taking place in Rwanda. They are accused of collaborating with the RPF and its murder or Habyarimana and taking advantage of the "docility" of the Rwandan people. The Rwandan people are in turn praised for their "fierce defense" which ensures that they will "never again" be enslaved as they were before the Revolution of 1959.
  - AV/922, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW075A)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 18
    This tape begins with an interview of an unidentified Minister by an unidentified journalist. The Minister attempts to give an explanation for the massacres that have taken place since Habyarimana's death. He then urges the population to work with the Army and their local authorities. A statement from the Ministry of Defense follows with accusations of atrocities committed by the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF). Gaudence Nyirahabimana, President of the MFBP is next with a statement supporting the new government. Side A ends with an interview of Sixbert Ndayambaje, burgomaster of Runda, in which he offers evidence of an RPF infrastructure in Rwanda. Bamwanga adds a direct call against Karekezi, a printer in Kigali.
  - AV/922, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW075B)
    This tape includes the conclusion to the interview with Sixbert Ndayambaje, the burgomaster of Runda commune, from Archive #075A. Ndayambaje explains that the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF)'s plans involve killing people as a necessary means to obtaining power. The interview is then broadcasted in French and focuses on the RPF's having established a network within Rwanda's borders. An unidentified journalist follows with news bulletins and a letter from the "Association of those who love Rwanda" calling for cooperation between the government, military, and citizens, and criticizing the RPF. The tape ends with a statement from the "Intikiza" with a call for an end to the fighting.
  - av/923, Sony HF 60 (Box 120, Audio-cassette RW076)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 19
  - AV/925, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW078)
    Cette cassette est entièrement composée d'une discussion entre le journaliste Bicamumpaka, Murego du MDR, Ngirumpatse du MRND, Mbonampeka du PL et Nsengiyumva du PSD. Suivant l'introduction de Bicamumpaka, dans laquelle il explique que le Rwanda vie des moments difficiles à cause de la guerre déclenchée par le FPR, la discussion se poursuit sur ces thèmes: (1) le FPR fait preuve de son orgueil en refusant de reconnaître le nouveau gouvernement Rwandais et le FPR est accusé d'avoir déjà assassiné de hautes personnalités Rwandaises, (2) le FPR a l'intention de restaurer la monarchie d'antan, (3) défendre les personnes qui ont été victimes des massacres suivant l'assassinat de Habyarimana n'est qu'un prétexte pour masquer leur propre but d'exterminer la population, (4) le FPR est accusé d'avoir assassiné le Président Habyarimana, (5) le FPR avait préparé la reprise de la guerre depuis longtemps et s'étaient infiltrés parmi la population, (6) la guerre d'aujourd'hui n'est qu'une continuation de la révolution de 1959, (7) les Inkotanyi vont se faire exterminer car la population Rwandaise refusera de subir le règne du FPR, (8) la population doit veiller contre les complices qui se sont infiltrés grâce au gouvernement précédent.
  - AV/927, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW079)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 21
  - AV/928, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW080A)
    This tape consists of Bamwanga's interview with political party leaders Karemera (MRND), Mbonyumutwa (MDR), Mbonampeka (PL), and Nsengiyumva (PSD). They discuss the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF)'s true motives behind its claim that it is only fighting the Presidential Guards and the Interahamwe-CDR. Bamwanga also asks the party leaders to discuss why the RPF appears concerned with the deaths of former Hutu politicians. The four men generally agree that the RPF is interested only in obtaining power and in disguising their "Inyenzi" and UNAR origins.
  - AV/928, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW080B)
    This tape has the second half of Bamwanga's interview from Archive #080A with political party leaders Karemera (MRND), Mbonyumutwa (MDR), Mbonampeka (PL), and Nsengiyumva (PSD). They continue their discussion about the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF)'s motives when it defends the cause of dead Hutu politicians. Bamwanga and the party leaders also address the RPF's call to Rwandans to join them before "it is too late." Again there is general agreement that the RPF is interested only in obtaining power and that the RPF is attempting to "trick" and mislead people. The men also suggest that the RPF is appealing to the population because it fears it will lose the war.
  - AV/930, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW081)
  - AV/931, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW082)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 23
    Un journaliste non-identifié commence la cassette avec une déclaration que les forces armées du FPR "massacrent systématiquement" la population Rwandaise. Il ajoute que le FPR est responsable de l'assassinat du Président Habyarimana et que la population doit collaborer avec la FAR pour combattre l'infiltration des Inkotanyi. Ce journaliste est suivi d'un entretien de Froduald Karamira du MDR par Nkundibiza. Karamira annonce que les "Inyenzi" se trouvant à Kigali se font arrêtés par la population aux barrières. Il annonce aussi qu'il ne reste plus que Nyanza, Rebero et Kacyiru a nettoyé. Karamira dit à la population de ne pas se mettre engroupe car les Inkotanyi sont capables de tirer dans la foule. Il accuse le FPR de vouloir exterminer la population et qu'il faut donc donner une formation à la population pour qu'elle puisse se défendre. Karamira ajoute que les Inkotanyi font exterminer les Tutsi car ils ont fait de cette guerre une guerre ethnique. Rwakana prend la relève et s'entretient avec plusieurs citoyens Rwandais à Kigali. Ces Rwandais rapportent que les Inkotanyi font des masscres un peu partout dans le pays. Certains ajoutent que les routes sont pleins de cadavres d'Inkotanyi aussi. Un journaliste non-identifié annonce que le FPR refuse de prendre sa place aux négociations sans que le gouvernement Rwandais mette fin aux massacres.
  - AV/932, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW083)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 24
    Cette cassette annonce le départ d'une majorité des troupes de la MINUAR et le début des négociations avec le FPR. Un journaliste loue les efforts de la population et annonce que les Inkotanyi ont de plus en plus de difficultés à s'échapper de Kigali. A plusieurs reprises le FPR est accusé d'avoir perpétré des massacres contre des civiles Rwandais. La cassette contient aussi deux entrtiens: l'un avec le Secrétaire Général Adjoint de la Croix Rouge Internationale, Paul Greet Rider, et l'autre avec le Ministre d'Information, Eliezer Niyitegeka. Niyitegeka explique que les 13.000 réfugiés qui se trouvent au Stade Amahoro, à l'Hôpital Faycal et aux Hôtels Méridien et Milles Collines doivent être identifiés avant de pouvoir partir vers des lieux plus sûrs. Il insinue aussi que la question de la légitimité du gouvernement Rwandais est sans base et que ce gouvernement est reconnu par la communauté internationale aussi bien que par l'O.N.U.
  - RTLM/30, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW084)
    Air Date: 1994 June 10
    Bemeriki maintient que l'installation des institutions de transition n'a pas été accompli parce que les "Inyenzi Inkotanyi" ont re-déclenché la guerre. Elle interview Jean-Pierre Kajuga de la commune Murambi qui rapporte que la préfecture de Byumba est devenu "un repaire des soldats de Museveni." Kajuga explique qu'un comité a été formé pour se charger de "l'autodéfense" et que chaque personne doit se servir des armes même si ce ne sont que des armes traditionnelles. Bemeriki rapporte ensuite que la presse internationale "a avoué" que les "Inyenzi" ont tué des religieux et que le Pape est déconcerté. Ananie prend son tour au micro et explique que la communauté internationale continue à rapporter des informations erronées obtenues des Inkotanyi. Un journaliste non-identifié rapporte que 650.000 Hutu sont morts à Byumba et 500.000 sont morts à Kibungo. Bemeriki reprend le micro et commence une discussion avec Bernard Hategekimana qui travail au journal "Kamarampaka." Les deux journalistes sont d'accord que les forces armées Rwandaises "ont la situation en main" et que les habitants qui avaient fui devant l'avance Inkotanyi sont revenus. Hategekimana explique que les Inkotanyi continue à lancer des bombes sur la population. Bemeriki, Bernard Mukwiye et Ananie terminent la cassette. Ils s'adressent à la situation à Gisenyi où la population a été "sensibilisé," et à la propagande des Inkotanyi qui veulent que les Rwandais se disputent entre nord et sud.
  - RTLM 21, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW085)
    Air Date: 1994 June 5
  - RTLM 27, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW086)
  - RTLM 5, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW087)
    Air Date: 1994 May 17
  - RTLM, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW088)
  - Georges Ruggiu sur les autres de la RTLM, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW089)
  - Interahmwena Escarid de la Mort, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW090)
    Air Date [not available]
  - Statement #12, Sony Super EF 60 (2 copies (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW091 and RW092)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 20
  - La commune sur telephone, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW093)
  - Radio Rwanda, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW094)
  - RTLM, Sony Super EF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW096)
    Air Date: 1993 Oct. 25
    Hitimana commence cette cassette avec une défense de la RTLM qu'il dit est faussement accusé de vouloir semer la mésentente. Il continue son monologue en adressant ces thèmes: (1) les Hutu doivent se réunir est former un collectif semblable à celui des Tutsi, (2) un message du MDR qui soutient la RTLM, (3) l'annonce d'une marchr de chagrin au Burundi. Kantano prend le micro ensuite et déclare que: (1) les Tutsi "mangeurs du chien" ont assassiné le Président Burundais Ndadaye, (2) les Tutsi ont des tendances exterminatrices, (3) le Premier Ministre Uwilingiyimana collabore avec les complices Inkotanyi, (4) les Tutsi sont des sanguinaires. Hitimana reprend le micro et interview des infirmes et un docteur à l'hôpital des forces armées cette "journée de l'armée." L'effet de l'entretien est de démontré le niveau de souffrance qui est le résultat de cette guerre déclenchée par les Inkotanyi. Hitimana termine l'émission en accusant les Inkotanyi d'avoir tué 70 élèves à l'Ecole Normale de Kirimbi dans la province de Gitega.
  - No title, Sony Super EF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW097)
    Air Date: 1993 Oct. 29
  - RTLM, Sony HF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW098)
    Air Date: 1993 Nov. 12
  - RTLM, Sony Super EF 60 (Box 121, Audio-cassette RW099A)
    Air Date: 1993 Nov. 20